Estefano Matías **Muñoz Moya**

Ph.D. BIOMECHANICS STUDENT • EARLY STAGE RESEARCHER • DISC4ALL ITN MARIE SKŁODOWSKA-CURIE ACTIONS

🗷 estefano.munoz@usach.cl | 🎢 estefano23.github.io | 🖸 0000-0001-5222-4071 | 🔞 Estefano-Munoz-Moya | 🖸 estefano23 | 🛅 estefano-munoz-moya

Presentation _

Ph.D. student in the Disc4All MSCA-ITN as an early stage researcher (ESR), and Master's degree in Mechanical Engineering. Researchers in biomechanics and biomaterials focused on experimental and numerical work, numerical methods, solid mechanics, finite element method, and continuum mechanics. Responsible, proactive, with excellent learning capacity, empathetic with others, tolerant to failure, and work under pressure.

Education

Universitat Pompeu Fabra (UPF)

Barcelona, Spain

DOCTORAL DEGREE | IN PROGRESS

Oct. 2021 - **PRESENT**

• Ph.D. Information and Communication Technologies.

Universidad de Santiago de Chile (USACH)

BACHELOR DEGREE | AWARDED | GPA: 6.2/7.0

Santiago, Chile

MASTER DEGREE | AWARDED | GPA: 6.9/7.0 | HIGHEST DISTINCTION

2018 - 2020

• M.Sc. Mechanical Engineering | Diploma Link

2012 202

- Professional Degree Civil Mechanical Engineering | Diploma Link
- B.Sc. Mechanical Engineering | Diploma Link

Work Experience __

Universitat Pompeu Fabra (UPF) | Disc4All Project (Disc4All)

Barcelona, Spain

EARLY STAGE RESEARCHER (ESR) | DISC4ALL MSCA-2020-ITN-ETN GA: 955735 | Ph. D. JÉRÔME NOAILLY

Oct. 2021 - **PRESENT**

- $\bullet \ \ \text{Project: } \textit{Training network to advance integrated computational simulations in translational medicine, applied to intervertebral \textit{disc degeneration.}}$
- Numerical computational research on intervertebral discs under disc degeneration.

Universidad de Santiago de Chile (USACH), Departamento de Ingeniería Mecánica (DIMEC)

Santiago, Chile

PART-TIME TEACHER: Engineering Drawing | THEORY.

PART-TIME TEACHER: Strength of Materials | Laboratory.

Apr. 2021 - Aug. 2021 Apr. 2021 - Aug. 2021

PART-TIME TEACHER: Introduction to Mechanical Engineering | THEORY.

Apr. 2021 - Aug. 2021 Oct. 2020 - Mar. 2021

Part-time Teacher: Computational Mechanical Design | Theory.
Part-time Teacher: Engineering Drawing | Laboratory.

Oct. 2020 - Mar. 2021

Universidad Santo Tomás (UST) | Centre for Climate Change Research and Innovation (CiiCC)

Santiago, Chile Oct. 2018 - Jun. 2021

RESEARCH ASSISTANT | PROJECT PIA-ANID ANILLO ACT 172037 | Ph. D. Nelson A. Lagos

- Project: Interacting structure and function of ecological, mechanical and mineralogical properties of marine calcifiers: Shell carbonates as sources
 of bio-inspiration (Carbo-Nat-Lab).
- Experimental and numerical computational research on the shell skeleton structure from the Chilean coast, subject to climate change scenarios.

Universidad de Santiago de Chile (USACH) | Lab. de Biomecáncia y Biomateriales (BioMatLab)

Santiago, Chile

RESEARCH ASSISTANT | PROJECT FONDECYT 1170608F | PH. D. CLAUDIO M. GARCÍA-HERRERA | PH. D. DIEGO J. CELENTANO

Oct. 2018 - Jun. 2021

- Project: Biomechanical Behaviour of Arteries from Chronic Hypoxic Animals: Experiments, Modelling, Numerical Simulation and Validation.
- Biomechanical characterization of arteries to observe adverse effects, such as hypoxia suffered by Chilean mining workers. In collaboration with the veterinary medical center of the University of Chile.

Universidad de Santiago de Chile (USACH), Departamento de Ingeniería Mecánica (DIMEC)

Santiago, Chile

TEACHING ASSISTANCE: Introduction to Mechanical Engineering.

Mar. 2020 - Sep. 2020 Mar. 2019 - Aug. 2019

TEACHING ASSISTANCE: Strength of Materials.
TEACHING ASSISTANCE: Applied Mathematics.

Aug. 2019 - Aug. 2019 Aug. 2018 - Aug. 2019

TEACHING ASSISTANCE: Thermal Systems (Thermodynamics II).

Jul. 2017 - Jan. 2019

• Teaching assistance and development of educational guides/tests and resources.

Publications | estefano23.github.io/publications.html_

PUBLISHED | FRONTIERS: CELL AND DEVELOPMENTAL BIOLOGY | DOI 10.3389/FCELL.2022.924692

Co-Author | 2022

• Immuno-Modulatory Effects of Intervertebral Disc Cells.

PUBLISHED | SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | DOI 10.1038/S41598-021-04414-1

First Author | 2022

• Evaluation of remodeling and geometry on the biomechanical properties of nacreous bivalve shells.

Biomechanical Characterization of Scallop Shells Exposed to Ocean Acidification and Warming.

First Author | 2022

• Towards a repository of patient-specific intervertebral disc finite element models

IN PROGRESS First Author | 2022

Mussel shells under predation attacks: biomechanical characterization and numerical simulations using finite element analysis

Conferences estefano23.github.io/work.html#conferences_

VPHi Conference (VPHi 2022), Universidade do Porto.

UPORTO, Porto, Portugal

INTERNATIONAL | POSTER PRESENTATION | CERTIFICATE LINK | POSTER LINK

Sep. 2022

TOWARDS A REPOSITORY OF PATIENT-SPECIFIC INTERVERTEBRAL DISC FINITE ELEMENT MODELS.

27° Congress of the European Society of Biomechanics (ESB 2022), Universidade do Porto.

UPORTO, Porto, Portugal

International | Speaker Presentation | Certificate Link | Podium Certificate Link

Jun. 2022

• TOWARDS A REPOSITORY OF PATIENT-SPECIFIC INTERVERTEBRAL DISC FINITE ELEMENT MODELS.

6th Barcelona VPH Summer School (VPH SC 2022), Universitat Pompeu Fabra.

UPF, Barcelona, Spain

INTERNATIONAL | POSTER PRESENTATION | CERTIFICATE LINK | POSTER LINK

May. 2022

TOWARDS A REPOSITORY OF PATIENT-SPECIFIC INTERVERTEBRAL DISC FINITE ELEMENT MODELS.

IX International Conference on Computational Bioengineering (ICCB 2022), ULisboa.

ULisboa, Lisboa, Portugal

INTERNATIONAL | SPEAKER PRESENTATION | CERTIFICATE LINK

• TOWARDS A REPOSITORY OF PATIENT-SPECIFIC INTERVERTEBRAL DISC FINITE ELEMENT MODELS.

X Capítulo Español: Sociedad Europea de Biomecánica (ESB-ESP 2022), Universidad de Granada.

UGR, Granada, Spain

Apr. 2022

SPAIN | SPEAKER PRESENTATION | CERTIFICATE LINK

Oct. 2021

 COMPORTAMIENTO BIOMECÁNICO DE LAS CONCHAS DE LOS MEJILLONES: DEGRADACIÓN DURANTE LA REMODELACIÓN DE LAS PROPIEDADES MECÁNICAS Y SISTEMA DE DEFENSA.

XL Congreso de Ciencias del Mar, Universidad de Magallanes, SCHCM.

UMAG, Magallanes, Chile, Virtual

CHILE | SPEAKER PRESENTATION | CERTIFICATE LINK

May. 2021

COMPORTAMIENTO MECÁNICO SIMÉTRICO DE LA RESISTENCIA DE LAS CONCHAS DEL MEJILLÓN PERUMYTILUS PURPURATUS.

11° World Biomaterials Congress (WBC 2020), University of Glasgow, IUSBSE.

Glas, Glasgow, Scotland, Virtual

INTERNATIONAL | POSTER PRESENTATION | CERTIFICATE LINK | POSTER LINK

Dec 2020

MECHANICAL BEHAVIOR SYMMETRY OF MUSSEL SHELLS AND NUMERICAL METHOD FOR BIOMATERIAL ORTHOTROPY DIRECTIONS.

2° Congreso de Estudiantes de Postgrado USACH (USACH 2020), Universidad de Santiago de Chile.

USACH, Santiago, Chile, Virtual

CHILE | SPEAKER PRESENTATION | CERTIFICATE LINK

Nov. 2020

PERUMYTILUS PURPURATUS: SIMETRÍA DE VALVAS Y CARACTERIZACIÓN DE DIRECCIÓN ORTÓTROPA.

Congreso Chileno de Biomecánica y Biomateriales (CBIO 2020), Universidad de Santiago de Chile.

USACH, Santiago, Chile, Virtual

CHILE | SPEAKER PRESENTATION | ORGANIZER | CERTIFICATE LINK

Oct. 2020

PERUMYTILUS PURPURATUS: SIMETRÍA DE VALVAS Y CARACTERIZACIÓN DE DIRECCIÓN ORTÓTROPA.

Congreso Internacional de Metalurgia y Materiales (CONAMET 2019), Universidad Austral de Chile.

UACH. Valdivia. Chile

INTERNATIONAL | SPEAKER PRESENTATION | CERTIFICATE LINK

Nov. 2019

ANÁLISIS DE LA RESPUESTA BIOMECÁNICA DE PERUMYTILUS PURPURATUS ANTE ESCENARIOS DE CAMBIO CLIMÁTICO.

1º Congreso de Estudiantes de Postgrado USACH (USACH 2019), Universidad de Santiago de Chile.

Aug. 2019

USACH, Santiago, Chile

CHILE | SPEAKER PRESENTATION | CERTIFICATE LINK

• MODELOS CONSTITUTIVOS DE CRECIMIENTO APLICADOS A LA CONCHA DEL PERUMYTILUS PURPURATUS.

25° Congress of the European Society of Biomechanics (ESB 2019), TU Wien.

TU Wien, Vienna, Austria Jul. 2019

INTERNATIONAL | 2 SPEAKER PRESENTATIONS | CERTIFICATE LINK

- BIOMECHANICAL BEHAVIOUR ON SHELL CHARACTERISTICS (PERUMYTILUS PURPURATUS) ALONG THE CHILEAN COAST.
- NUMERICAL ANALYSIS OF THE BIOMECHANICAL RESPONSE OF OYSTER SHELLS SUBJECTED TO CLIMATE CHANGE SCENARIOS.

5th VPH Summer School: Stratification of patients with complex phenotypes

Universitat Pompeu Fabra, Virtual

TRAINING PROGRAM | STUDENT | CERTIFICATE LINK

Jun. 2021

• Transversal training of in silico medicine. Dictated by BCN MedTech, Virtual Physiological Human Institute (VPHi), and QUAES Foundation.

POSTGRADUATE COURSE | STUDENT | CERTIFICATE LINK

Nov 2018

• Dictated by the academics Ph. D. Antonio Checa (Universidad de Granada, Spain) and Ph. D. Fabio Labra (Universidad Santo Tomás, Chile).

Memberships _

Virtual Physiological Human institute (VPHi)

Europe

STUDENT MEMBER | CERTIFICATE LINK Sep. 2022 - PRESENT

· Membership UPF

European Society of Biomechanics (ESB)

Europe

STUDENT MEMBER | CERTIFICATE LINK

Jul. 2020 - **PRESENT**

• Membership ID: 3263

STEM Preeschoolar USACH-DIMEC (Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics)

Santiago, Chile

MEMBER | CERTIFICATE LINK

Oct. 2019 - **PRESENT**

- Scientific popularization for preschool children with a gender perspective.

Awards

6th Barcelona VPH Summer School (VPH SC 2022), Universitat Pompeu Fabra (UPF).

Barcelona, Spain

BEST HANDSON | CERTIFICATE LINK

May. 2022

• HandsOn: Surrogate modeling of IVD simulation under physiological sports loading conditions.

European Union to study in Universitat Pompeu Fabra (UPF).

Barcelona, Spain

SCHOLARSHIP | CERTIFICATE LINK

Oct. 2013 - 2021

• Full Ph.D. scholarship. EARLY STAGE RESEARCHER DISC4ALL ITN MARIE SKŁODOWSKA-CURIE ACTIONS

Government of Chile to study in University of Santiago de Chile (USACH).

Santiago, Chile

Scholarship | CERTIFICATE LINK

Oct. 2018 - 2020

• Full Master scholarship. BECA ARANCEL

Government of Chile to study in University of Santiago de Chile (USACH).

Santiago, Chile

SCHOLARSHIP | CERTIFICATE LINK

Oct. 2013 - 2021

• Full Undergraduate scholarship. BECA BICENTENARIO

Science Popularization.

Science Festival - Festival de la Ciencia (FECI of PAR Explora RM Sur Poniente), Universidad de Chile

UCHILE, Virtual

EXPERT SCIENTIFIC COLLABORATOR | CERTIFICATE LINK

Nov. 2020

• Science experiments for children.

Science Festival - 10° Feria Científica USACH, Universidad de Santiago de Chile

USACH, Santiago, Chile

EXPERT SCIENTIFIC COLLABORATOR | CERTIFICATE LINK

Oct. 2019

• Exhibition of biomechanical tests for children.

Exhibition - Mollusca, espiral del cambio - CiiCC, Museo de Historia Natural de Valparaíso (MHNV)

MHNV, Valparaíso, Chile

EXPERT SCIENTIFIC COLLABORATOR | CERTIFICATE LINK

EXPERT SCIENTIFIC COLLABORATOR | CERTIFICATE LINK

Oct. 2019

• Exhibition of the consequences of climate change in the oceans.

ile

PARQUEMET, Santiago, Chile

Exhibition - XII Fiesta de la ciencia y la tecnología (PAR Explora RM Sur Oriente), Universidad de Chile

Oct. 2018

· Exhibition of the mechanical properties of the mollusk shells subject to climate change scenarios.



Full name: Estefano Matías Muñoz Moya

BASIC INFORMATION

- Birth: 23th of September of 1994 | Santiago, RM, Republic of Chile | Age: 26 years old
- email: estefano.munoz.moya@gmail.com
- Lenguages: Native Spanish | Advanced English

PROGRAMMING LENGUAGES AND SOFTWARE USAGE

- Programming lenguages: : Fortran | Python | Matlab/Octave | C/C++ | HTML |
- Software usage: In-House FEM Softwares | AutoCAD | Solidworks | Ansys | Inventor | Mathcad | Fusion360 | SAM | Latex | Arduino | Ubuntu | EDEM | GiD | InVesalius | Office (Word, PowerPoint, Excel, Project) |

References

Ph. D. Jérôme Noailly | ResearchGate Link, Principal investigator, ESR supervision, and project coordinator of Disc4All - Universitat Pompeu Fabra (UPF). email: jerome.noailly@upf.edu

Ph. D. Claudio M. García-Herrera | ResearchGate Link, Director of the Mechanical Engineering Department, Associated Professor, and Researcher - University of Santiago de Chile (USACH). email: claudio.garcia@usach.cl

Ph. D. Nelson A. Lagos | ResearchGate Link, Director of the Centre for Climate Change Research and Innovation (Cii/CC), Associated Professor, and Researcher - Santo Tomás University (UST). email: nlagoss@santotomas.cl

Ph. D. Diego J. Celentano | ResearchGate Link, Full Professor and Researcher of Mechanical and Metallurgical Engineering Department, Pontifical Catholic University of Chile (PUC Chile). email: dcelentano@ing.puc.cl